<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<xeno:space xmlns:xeno="xeno:XENOmat" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/">

    <!-- HOW TO BUILD AN INFORMATION SYSTEM FROM (ALMOST) SCRATCH -->

    <intro>
        If you were to start from scratch, what would you "really need" in
        order to build an information system that minimises resource usage?
        
        To answer that question with at least some accuracy, we must first
        define what "information system" and "minimises resource usage" is
        supposed to mean. We shall have a look at these terms in isolation
        and begin by discussing resources and their use.
        
        There are many meanings to the word "resource", but common to them
        is that they all are associated with some kind of costs. Hence our
        focus on resource usage will be quite broad, and take into account
        both the economics of software development and the energy usage of
        the physical system.
        
        Planning, implementing, testing, deploying, and maintenance of any
        system requires time, skilled people, and a working infrastructure.
        
        A running system requires energy.
        
        One of the most compelling reasons to focus on resource usage is that 
        being energy savings in mobile or remote devices. Another reason
        is the inherent value of having a well defined cost of computation.
        
        Your smartphone does not function for free... It needs energy, and 
        you have to charge it. If you happen to have a solar charger, you're 
        home free, but certainly there is a price for having such a system
        running. For the software ecosystem follows, that apps which drain 
        our smartphones will be outperformed by apps that don't.
        
        Apart from electricity, the human and technical resources used for 
        developing systems are a big factor in this age of IoT. Increasing 
        complexity in "modern systems" literaly drains out a lot of potential 
        from the IT sector. There still is a huge demand for developers and 
        operators, and the complexity is ever increasing, as we see it.
        
        Now, it should be important to acknowledge, that much of this complexity 
        comes from a wrong line of thinking.
        
        In order to grasp this very problem, that a fresh start on the concept 
        of "computing" would solve, we have to define more precisely, what our
        quest is. What does our goal imply?
        
        Minimal resource usage, check. We have that covered by having a well
        defined cost of computation and by following a few basic principles. 
        But information systems? Well, that depends...
        
        <!-- So, what is information? -->
        
        The core question we need to address first, is: What is the stuff
        called 'information' actually? The 'system' part we shall address
        later.
        
        Throughout history, philosophers and scientists have come up with 
        different definitions. A classic paper on the subject was written 
        by Claude Shannon back in 1948, in which 'information' is thought 
        of as a set of possible messages sent over a channel.
        
        Titled "A Mathematical Theory of Communication", Shannon's theory
        as well as the field of 'information theory' which it spawned, is
        still quite narrow in its scope of defining what information is:
        
        It has its focus solely on individual pieces of technology within 
        given systems.
        
        In contrast, the broad interdisciplinary field named 'information 
        science' has a wider take on 'information systems'. It does focus
        on understanding problems of the stakeholders involved from their
        point of view, and then using information and other technology to 
        tackle those systemic problems. It's about communication.
        
        For the purpose of this text, we shall be using a definition given 
        by the late British scientist and polymath Gregory Bateson. In his
        "Steps to an Ecology of Mind: Collected Essays in Anthropology", 
        Bateson makes number of attempts to understand the mental processes 
        that are involved in making sense of surrounding world, and in this 
        context, he defines the basic unit of information as being 
        "a difference, that makes a difference".

        <!-- Doing simple stuff with information -->
        
        This conception of information is a nice fit for our purposes. It 
        also gives us the right to abstain from using complicated language.
        
        Keeping things simple has always been a good rule for making artefacts 
        that actually do work. Making things overly complex is a recipy for
        failure, as the ingenious Charles Babbage miserably had to experience,
        in his bold plan to build an analytic engine.
        
        Also, using complicated wording seldom will add any value at all in 
        solving the problems at hand. Doing so anyway is a one of the worst
        anti patterns - the equivalent to adding several abstraction layers, 
        that do nothing but passing data between layers. Because we can.
        
        <aside>
        Some of you developers may remember the first Windows NT, Microsofts 
        at that time new operating system, whose architects had built on top
        top of an Hardware Abstraction Layer (HAL). That decision sucked all 
        performance out of the system, until Microsoft finally started to 
        break it up again with APIs for direct access to the hardware. Then 
        their OS'es started to kick to the metal again.
        
        This anti pattern is also found in many system architecture frameworks,
        by which developers get coerced into using asynchronous communication 
        patterns, even for implementing protocols which are of a rather
        synchronous nature.

        What mostly happens, is that developers find themselves adding a lot of 
        boilerplate code with the sole purpose of being sure that everything is 
        synchronised.
        
        Because. Humans mostly like to have information presented in order, and 
        need (often enforced by national laws) a minimum of information to make 
        a decision on how to proceed and succeed within the system.
        
        Hence such (inter)actions simply must be synchronised ("for the record")
        for us in order to be able to decide anything on cause and effect.
        </aside>
        
        <!-- How to represent information -->
        
        As a last note on the concept of "information" as we like to use it in
        the "real world", it is essential to remember that in order to grasp 
        information, to make use of available information, there has to be some 
        sort of mechanism which will react on these "differences".

        This goes for any stakeholder in a system, whether it is a human being
        or some cloud service.
        
        In the field of computer systems, that basic difference is the bit.
        The smallest piece of information we can communicate is the difference 
        between "something" and "nothing". A sound from a speaker, as opposed
        to silence, or a light that suddenly starts flashing, when it was lit
        constantly before. Or some pixels on a display, which constantly change
        to form letters and symbols, which can be read by literate humans. As 
        you do now.
        
                       Differences are, what convey meaning.
                       
        <aside>
        Developers can freely interpret Bateson's definition in a resource 
        centred fashion, and adhere to a number of best DevOps practices.
        
        One of those practices is fetching resources via a cache. This is 
        done in order to reduce both network bandwith and needed (or must
        we say wasted?) computational power when "nothing really happened", 
        when no information has changed.
        
        Burning battery power without actually making a difference is not 
        something you'd want. At all. Ever. Systems exposing that behaviour 
        actually can be seen to be in some state of in-difference, a condition 
        which also (not surprisingly) seems to lead to human burnout syndromes 
        in social systems.
        </aside>

                        The representation is all there is.

        Using Bateson's definition of "information", you would then need to 
        have a way to describe the system. A kind of blueprint with sufficient 
        information for enabling someone or something to actually build the 
        system, or for some software to emulate the processes needed for the 
        system to actually fulfill its purpose.

        As in time of writing, contemporary object-oriented programmers commonly
        create some kind of "model" by writing definitions of concepts in special 
        languages like Python, Java, C#, Ruby, and (more or less) briefly describe 
        a system in terms of interacting objects.

        Other approaches exist too. A system may be described by functions,
        taking input, calculating output. Some languages even blur the 
        distinction between objects and functions.
        
        An interesting angle on the subject can be found in the area of actor 
        languages. Communicating entities, where a program is described pretty 
        much as a script for acting out a play in a theatre or a movie:
        
          BRAIN to LIVER: are you guys sleeping or what? I have blurry vision.
          LIVER to BRAIN: then stop slamming those G&amp;T's down.
            
        All in all, on the internet there is a whole bunch of esoteric languages, 
        so feel free to dive into that on your own. Enough has been written about 
        those subjects already, and we shall not further in this text discuss it,
        as we anyway are going to take another, different approach on computation.
        
        <!-- The power of spatial metaphors -->

        This other approach (which even predates most programming languages, as 
        we know them) was originally concepted by Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz back
        in the 16th century. Only much later, just prior to World War II, it was 
        taken into reality by Konrad Zuse, the German engineer who (with focused
        patience and quite limited resources) did build some of the worlds first 
        working electronic computers. Several thousand electrical switches, each 
        of which were painstakingly handcrafted out of copper and iron.

        But those machines he built, was not his only achievements. Zuse imagined 
        that the universe could be described at what he called "Rechnender Raum".
        A "computing universe," where actions in the real world are thought of as 
        discrete changes in state and transfer of information. This is a thought, 
        which we can easily be identified as a precursor to a relative new branch 
        in the science of physics, known as "Digital Physics", or "DP" for short.
        
        Without getting into the nitty-gritty details of DP, one of the important
        findings in this particular area are the class of cellular automata built 
        on "conservative logic," a basis for developing energy conserving digital 
        logic machines.
        
        This turns out to be useful for our quest, as the concepts of energy and
        information are strongly related. Look up Edward Fredkin and his work on 
        conservative logic, or Stephen Wolframs work on cellular automata if you 
        are interested in that area.
        
        We will attempt an approach in this direction in the following sections. 
        Let us begin by imagening the system as some kind of imaginary space, in
        which "there is information" or where "information can be found". 
        
        We can put information into that space, and get information out of there 
        as well.
        
        <!-- Organising and navigating space -->
        
        To easily locate that information, we shall (as we keep our wow of using 
        simple language) divide the space into a number of
        
        <places where-you-can="PUT">
            <information>

Now, the spatial, geographical metaphor is very present in our "Age of the Internet."
For instance, the information in this very XML document you are reading right now is 
stored in a file on some storage media, located inside some sort of computer. It's a 
place on the internet. Or was it "in the internet?"

Let's for a short moment assume, this document is the whole world, so our "space" is 
the text you are reading now. Moving through that world, you might at one point 
notice the very monotony of its linear nature, it's just words, words... Until you
notice a sign, which tells you have arrived at a new place.

For instance, part of this sentence, the one single word between <here> and </here>, 
is a canonical example of a very small place named "here."

It might be useful to regard those marks around the name "here" as some kind of 
place-sign, commonly found at city limits.

There may be <empty/> places as well. No need to write <empty></empty>. That would
simply be a sign, telling you that this point is called "empty", and there is nothing 
in here. It starts and stops at the same location.

Now, this text, this very paragraph, is located in a place called "information"
(see above) and you reached it by starting reading a place called "intro"
(at the start of the document), then going to "places" and finally to "information", 
where the author put this for you to read.

Using a simple notation, we can write the sequence of places entered, the "path" so 
to speak, by spelling out their names, separated with a slash:

<path>/intro/places/information/</path>

It may be useful to think of those slashes as gates or doors, through which you 
have entered the places. A path is just like what you often see as part of the 
"internet address" in your web browser, and it means roughly the same. A path
gives directions of where to find different

            </information>
            
            in different

        </places>.
        
        The place containing all places is simply called "the space".
                
        That should be quite straight-forward, so let's leave the
    </intro>.
    
    <!-- coffee break -->
    
    <services>
        The minimum an information system should be able to do (besides keep
        information in different places) would be to render that information
        accessible to those who need it. The system must fulfil its purpose.

        So throughout an "information space", there should be located a number 
        of locations, where there be services which can fulfil those needs of 
        information.
        
        First, if we need to be able to enter the space from the outside, it 
        might be useful to set up a service listening for HTTP requests on a 
        given port:
        
        <xeno:http host="localhost" port="8901" Access-Control-Allow-Origin="*"/>
        
        And to deliver information stored on disk, really fast:
        
        <xeno:disk mount="/public/data" method="send"/>
        
        Information may also be present in the description itself, and simply 
        needs to be copied:
        
        <message>
            <xeno:copy type="text/plain">Hello world!</xeno:copy>
        </message>
        
        And, to get started, you might need some simple
        
        <storage>
            <xeno:stash type="text/plain"> where you can put volatile information... </xeno:stash>
        </storage>

    </services>
    
     
    <!-- 
        For a running system we need the next place to display information.
        You might think of it as a browser seen from the "other" side,
        where any content you put into it shows up on a surface somewhere.
        
        Whereas a browser is requesting - that is pulling - a resource to 
        display in a window, the display service may be used for pushing 
        content to a window as well. A typical implementation will use some 
        kind of WebView, dependent on the platform.

        If we put some info into that place, it would show up on a display,
        just as if you had retreived the info with a browser.
     -->
    
    <display>
        <xeno:display type="text/xml+xhtml+svg"/>
    </display>
    
    <!-- 
        Also, we might want the system to be able to give a description 
        of itself. We call that description a "blueprint":
    -->
    
    <blueprint>
        <!-- serve the fancy interpretation really fast -->
        <xeno:disk mount="blueprint.html" method="send"/>
        <!--
        <xeno:copy src="blueprint.js"/>
        -->
        <service>
            <!-- or use the built in service for raw data only about this section -->
            <xeno:blueprint type="text/xml" src="/blueprint"/>
        </service>
    </blueprint>
    
    <wiki>
        <tiddlywiki>
            The text between elements could be TW markup...
            
            So this section is largely random thoughts and description 
            of *not* implemented features.
            
            !Scratchpad...
        </tiddlywiki>

        <!-- freeze the blueprint from the point referenced -->
        <xeno:blueprint freeze="/blueprint">
            <!-- all the contact ever will get is a description of lines 9-15-->
        </xeno:blueprint>

        Freezing the blueprint means adding 
        the used namespaces to the opening 
        tag of the returned fragment, as well 
        as tagging the default namespace on
        the returned blueprint with the host (which is 
        in the Host of the request per default)
        or otherwise the value of the 'host' attribute.
        
        Par example:

        <xeno:space>
            <defaults>
                <xeno:blueprint src="/" host="$Host" type="application/xml" style="xml"/>
                    We deliver the whole blueprint of the enclosing space (starting with
                    defaults in this space)
                <xeno:blueprint src="/" host="fixed.domain.example.org"/>
                    The source is taken from root and the namespace is tied to some fixed domain
            </defaults>
            <pure-development>
                <xeno:blueprint freeze="/" host="Host" type="application/xml" style="xml"/>                
            </pure-development>
        </xeno:space>
        
        <xeno:blueprint freeze="/blueprint">
        </xeno:blueprint>
        
    </wiki>
    <musings>
        <!-- Highly experimental, half finished sentences may occur -->
        <objects>
            <!-- An approach on object-oriented modelling -->
            <new>
                Given the following xeno:proto declaration, 
                you get a prototypical structure served at

                    /musings/objects/new/user

                in a number of languages, e.g. JSON

                    {
                        fullname: "Kurt Gödel",
                        username: "abc123",
                        password: "********",
                        bookmark: "/project/23/app/312/track/321/version/423",
                        favorite: [
                            "/project/23",
                            "/project/342/app/23/track/321",
                            "/project/23",
                        ],
                        
                    }

                or XML, which more or less is a plain copy of the protoypes
                inner structure:
                
                <xeno:proto>
                    <user
                        fullname="Kurt Gödel"
                        username="abc123"
                        password="********">
                        <!-- attributes may also be simple tags -->
                        <bookmark>/project/23/app/312/track/321/version/423</bookmark>
                        <!-- and more occurrences represent elements in a list/sequence -->
                        <favorite>/project/23</favorite>
                        <favorite>/project/342/app/23/track/321</favorite>
                        <favorite role="admin">/project/23/edit</favorite>
                        <!-- this class may be extended -->
                        <xeno:extend/>
                    </user>
                    <!-- this model may be extended -->
                    <xeno:extend/>
                </xeno:proto>
                
                You can also source a prototype from another system
                
                <xeno:proto src="http://tpa.trifork.com/models/BundleTagIdentifier"/>

                We may note as a fact, that the context, in which this object will be used, 
                actually knows that these data are prototypical. As an example, when we fetch 
                something from a place called /musings/objects/new/user/, then a bell should 
                ring loud and clear.
                
                Knowing this, a form could use the default values given in the prototype 
                as labels or placeholders. It also knows that it should "insert" the form 
                data, rather than "update" it.
                
                <xeno:form name="user" action="/path/to/user/database/insert" proto="/musings/new/user">
                    <input name="fullname" type="text" value="">Label (for this input)</input>
                    <!-- script some action -->
                    <script>
                        // this.form.submit = ...;
                        fullname.addEventHandler('focus', function() { 
                            this.placeholder = this.textContent
                            delete this.textContent
                        }, false);
                    </script>
                </xeno:form>

                A prototypical structure might be marked with some unique identification:
                
                <xeno:proto unique="uuid(@id)">
                    <unique-object>
                        <identity id="will-get-replaced-by-a-uuid"/>
                    </unique-object>
                </xeno:proto>

                <xeno:proto unique="uuid(name)">
                    <unique-named>
                        <name>will get replaced by the hash</name>
                    </unique-named>
                </xeno:proto>
                
            </new>
            
            <version2>
                <xeno:proto type="text/python" lang="python">
                class User:
                    fullname="Kurt Gödel"
                    username="abc123"
                    password="********"
                    # attributes may also be simple tags
                    bookmark="/project/23/app/312/track/321/version/423"
                    # and more occurrences of elementname represent elements in a list/sequence -->
                    favorite = [
                        "/project/23",
                        "/project/342/app/23/track/321",
                        "...",
                    ]
                    <xeno:extend/>
                    <!-- see below, also this model may be extended -->
                </xeno:proto>            
            </version2>
            
        </objects>
        
        <xeno:proto extend="this:/musings/objects/version2">
            <app-user extend="user">
                <identitiy provider="http://cookie-monster.com/kurt.goedel/"/>
                <!-- the Python class User is extended with an identity field -->
            </app-user>
            <!-- no further extensions allowed -->
        </xeno:proto>
        
        <xeno:proto extend="http://embedded-host:8901/leutert/pdm/channels">
            <signals is="channels">
            </signals>
        </xeno:proto>

        
<!-- This is the cursor:
        Select the line and move it up/down with CMD CTRL UP/DOWN
        
        This.is (the system which has been built by this blueprint)
        That.at (the system which sent the contact into this space)
        
        -->
        <echo>
            <xeno:proto type="text/plain">You sent:\n<xeno:copy src="that:/*"/>
            <!-- Comments like this are not included, contact gets delivered a copy of the 
                 payload of the contact along with everything --> in plain text.
            </xeno:proto>
        </echo>
        <whoami>
            <!-- access the attributes of the contact (often HTTP headers) -->
            <xeno:proto type="text/plain">
                You are a visitor from <xeno:copy src="that:@Origin"/>.
            </xeno:proto>
        </whoami>
        
        <clone-origin>
            
        </clone-origin>

        <database>
            <admin>
                <xeno:sql>SELECT 
                    <fullname>FULLNAME</fullname>, 
                    <username>USERNAME</username>,
                    <password>PASSWORD</password>
                          FROM USER WHERE FULLNAME="admin"
                </xeno:sql>
            </admin>
        </database>
        
        <xeno:sloppy>
            <!-- paths within this sector will be interpreted sloppy -->
            <context/>
            <content alt="contest"/>
            <consent/>
            <consens/>
            <contens alt="nonsens"/>
        </xeno:sloppy>
        
        <xeno:L337>
            <h3ll0>
                <w0rld><xeno:copy></xeno:copy></w0rld>
            </h3ll0>
        </xeno:L337>

        <recursive ns="this">

            In the context of a (name)space, a name is a string -- a finite sequence of characters.
            <aside>The Halting Problem tells us, that we can not decide if we are dealing with a name, 
            given only a sequence.</aside>

            The namespace handling in a xeno:space gives us a mapping from (UTF-8) strings to integers.
            Each place in a space has a name which then maps to an integer.
            The set of integers mapping to places such comprise to an alphabet of valid symbols.

            Once having this alphabet, the path from the root to a given element can be written as a 
            sequence of integers. Just like a sequence of characters are interpreted as a word, 
            a sequence of words will form a sentence. In a given (name)space, each place P therefore may
            be designated by a sentence, which contains exactly the words necessary to get to P from 
            anywhere within that (name)space. A contact from another (outer?) space will be able
            to reach P with just one sentence.

            Finding this sequence for each place in the space will then comprise to the set of sentences 
            which are valid designations in that space.
            
            Now each place also has a number of other unique caracteristics. For one, there is the 
            position of a place, as encountered in a linear traversal of the containing space. Counting
            from 0 that gives us a unique integer for each place in the space, and hence a mapping for each
            sentence.

        </recursive>
        
        <![CDATA[
        Mashup of form / user-agent / proxy / port
        - quite experimental
        ]]>
        
        <visitors>
            <!-- a visiting contact has an origin - sending it via a subprotocol works like a proxy -->
            <xeno:http proto="https" action="url:" Content-Type="application/x-www-form-urlencoded">
                <!-- fullname=Kurt Gödel&copy=false -->
            </xeno:http>
            <!-- Forms as a special kind of contact? -->
        </visitors>
        
        <!-- or rather -->
        <user-agent>
            <!-- a contact is sent to another context with part of the payload -->
            <xeno:contact href="http://other.example.info" method="PUT" src="that:/data/for/other/system"/>
        </user-agent>
        
        
        <!-- accessible via ws://host:8901/musings/events/topics -->
        <events>
            <xeno:ws size="100" Access-Control-Allow-Origin="trusted.dom.ain">
                <!-- max. 100 subscribers aka connections -->
                <topics>
                    <xeno:stash type="application/javascript">initialMessageForSubscribers</xeno:stash>
                </topics>
            </xeno:ws>
        </events>
    </musings>
</xeno:space>
